I think it's good when you're teaching
meditation to a group or you're
meditating with a group is to remind
everyone that two things and you've
heard me say it many times my first
teacher getting on dargah 1973 before
you were born he used to take a pencil
and he would break it you know and then
he would take ten pencils and he
couldn't break it and then he'd say
people meditating together is like ten
pencils you know stronger okay
people meditating on their own it's like
one pencil so meditating in a group can
be very powerful and it can help you a
lot okay
what's the downside what's the problem
meditating in a group somebody makes
noise okay Johnny gonna be done the word
for sound in Tibetan is done the word
for enemy is also done different
spelling but a sense in harmony sounds
the same so there's a joke that sound is
the enemy of meditation so when you're
meditating in a group where you teach
meditation to a group then it's a big
thing you know do the pencil thing first
talk about the pencil thing first
and then it's always good to talk about
positive things first and then say look
if you move in this meditation you're
gonna disturb all these other people you
know you're gonna shake them out of
their meditation okay so you have to try
to be extremely quiet during during a
group meditation and Chi and the mind
are connected right along same
chupa-chupa so if you move your body
your mind has to move your your
meditation will be disturbed
so you have to try to get in the habit
of sitting like a statue sitting like a
stone and look your minds full of seeds
right 65 are opening every second and we
all have a mixture of good season bad
seeds
okay that's why we're still here in this
world okay we're the stupid kids in the
class who never got to go to the next
class so if you're here and I'm I'm here
also you have good seeds and pansies or
you wouldn't be here
you'd be somewhere else so as you
meditate this bad seeds are gonna open
also and and you're gonna feel
something's gonna happen okay a fly is
gonna land on your nose or you know
you're gonna have start to have some
pain that you never had before are you
gonna start thinking about the boyfriend
in high school that you didn't think
about for thirty years and who hurt you
you know something's gonna happen
so a big part of meditation is just
being tough okay just being tough try
not to dad seats are gonna open okay and
just nobody has a perfect meditation
okay you think I do I don't you think
the person next to you does they don't
either okay but you have to fight with
it okay and you have to be tough all
right don't move if that boyfriend comes
for half an hour just try to kick him
out again okay and okay but don't give
up okay and we talked about the three
goals of ACA and the big one was you
know go out and look at the Stars how
many people looked at the stars last
night yeah pretty cool we had some moon
the moon blanks them out a little bit
better
you know the big goal is to help
billions of planets okay and you will
never see them
if you don't meditate and and you will
die without knowing what's going on in
the world okay so you don't have much
choice it's the only way to see those
things is to meditate okay and you will
if you meditate you will see those
things and that changes you forever okay
then you become a fanatic non-phonetic a
CIA teacher okay and it would be a shame
in your life if you didn't see those
things and you could have just because
you didn't want to sit down every day
you know what I mean so your phone is
important WeChat is very important you
know porn chicks aren't important what's
punching a Russian donut okay Trudeau yo
Chou why I know this word in every
language okay those are important things
but to see billions of planets and
billions of beings and to love them to
have that experience once in your life
it's worth it right so let's try okay
let's go and the meditation we're gonna
do connects to the teaching you're gonna
get this week then the next section in
the Lum room
okay here we go
so your eyes are lightly closed if
you're super sleepy you're trying to
meditate in the afternoon you can crack
your eyes open a little bit but don't
look at anything and it's useful to
meditate in front of something that is
plain like a wall that's colored all the
same color or in front of a sheet if you
choose to crack your eyes open that'll
keep you from focusing on anything they
say watch your nose but it doesn't mean
to look cross-eyed it doesn't mean to
actually look at the tip of your nose it
means to focus your eyes on the plane
the distance of your nose away from your
eyes so actually you're looking at
nothing if you choose to crack your eyes
open so if you get sleepy you might
experiment with cracking your eyes open
but not looking at anything it's
important when you teach meditation to
try to get people to relax their face
it's very natural when the mind focuses
that we tighten our face especially
between your eyebrows it's called Blue
Boar imagem in sanskrit and it's
important to keep that place wrinkle
free so check the spot between your
eyebrows loosening up
and another place where all of us get
tension is in the corners of your mouth
so relax the corners of your mouth I
like to say a little Mona Lisa smile if
you smell slightly the channels Ida and
Pingala in your on either side of your
nose loosen and then the meditation goes
better because the Chi is flowing check
your fingers are they clenched on your
hands tight or are they relaxed they're
in general there's two ways to hold your
stomach your whole life hmm
you can just let it stick out naturally
or you can slightly very slightly
tighten it and get in this habit of
slightly tightening the muscles of your
stomach when you're sitting in
meditation that loosens the lower back
it loosens the corresponding muscles on
the back side of the body
shoulders are a big place of tension in
a human being and you might experiment
with instead of holding your hands on
your knees you can pull them back a
little bit towards the middle of your
thighs and that opens up your shoulders
try to check if the shoulders are if one
shoulders tighter than another almost
all human beings have alignment problems
partly because we are right-handed or
left-handed so your whole life you tend
to use one arm more than the other and
then it twists your spine so try to make
your shoulders equal and press them back
just a little bit that's easier if you
pull your hands back on your thighs just
slightly if you have your hands on your
knees are over your knees there's a
tendency for their shoulders to collapse
in yoga if you keep your eyes dirty
right your gaze slightly above the
horizon as often as you can
during the yoga session it affects how
clearly you think and it affects how you
move so you can experiment with that
even with your eyes closed where where
are you putting your eyes after you
close your eyes so you have a choice you
can look down with your eyes closed but
when you do that it tends to darken the
mind and the mind gets sleepy if you
look way out it's gonna move prana in a
way that gets you a little bit agitated
but if you look slightly above the
horizon like you're looking you know
you're driving and you're looking for
something in the distance if the eyes
are slightly raised above level you'll
find that it it makes your mind more
positive so in yoga or even in
meditation with your eyes closed it's a
big difference big breakthrough if you
keep your eyes slightly raised do one
last check is the face relaxed are the
hands relaxed it's my stomach just
released hanging out or is it slightly
tucked in last check before you start
meditating
look for tension in the mouth in the
eyes between the eyebrows
and then we go to breathing so it's
traditional to go to breathing Abdullah
from the abhidharma kosher exhale Jun
then inhale loop so start watching your
breath in general it's good if you can
breathe through your nose but if you
have a cold or if it's difficult it's
fine to breathe through your mouth
as you breathe through your nose there's
a little trick you can do which is to
try to draw the breath up higher so of
course the breath goes through your
nostrils down to your lungs through your
throat but how much of the graph goes up
into your sinus cavities will make a
difference in your focus so see if you
can as you breathe in draw the breath
higher in the head and it opens up
cavities it gives you a more oxygen and
gives you more breath
traditional to count 10 breath and it's
very important to do it starting from
the exhale there's extra breath in your
lungs there's extra air in your lungs
unused oxygen called tidal tidal air and
if you're gonna meditate successfully
it's important to get all the air out
when you breathe so during these 10
breaths we can take the opportunity to
confirm that we are exhaling all the air
the lungs will naturally pause twice
during a breath pretty long after the
exhale and then for a shorter time after
the inhale during the exhale for
successful meditation try to breathe
past the pause so the lungs will pause
on the exhale at the end of the exhale
and then try to push out a little tiny
bit more air so be conscious of your
breathing breathing is autonomic we
don't think about it but as you meditate
the meditation will go much better if
you learn to push out the tidal air push
out the extra air that would stay in
your lungs on the exhale so I like to
tell people don't worry much about the
inhale your body will take care of that
it's automatic if we had to think to
inhale we'd be dead already
so don't worry about the inhale but be
very conscious after
the Yoga Sutras says long and fine
Sushma tumble and we'll start counting
breath on the exhale one and then on the
inhale pause accounting and then on the
exhale to tradition is that you count to
ten without thinking of anything else no
mental seeds are ripening at a rate of
65 per second to keep all 65 seats
thinking just about exhales and
breathing it's probably impossible for a
human being but see if in general you
can think about the breathing and try to
start shutting out the outside world
okay here we go ten breaths
traditionally if you get to like five
and that boyfriend from high school
comes back in your mind then you're
supposed to start over and if you're
very honest with yourself you may never
get to your meditation so try a few
times when you exhale properly it's the
prana flows better in your body and you
won't get loan loan condition low means
the tidal air
build-up because of the focusing of the
mind will start to affect your heart
you'll feel nervous
you feel distracted you get a special
headache called come come in Tibetan dry
headache and so if you get these
symptoms because of your meditation
slight anxiety in the heart a slight
pain in the heart or your breathing is
erratic
all right fingers start shaking or you
feel agitated because of meditation you
can fix most of these problems just by
exhaling properly throughout the
meditation so that's a good solution for
these nervous problems that come from
meditating for long periods of time if
you don't address that problem it will
get worse and worse so nice long happy
exhales conscious exhales
faces soft fingers are solved stomach is
not soft
keep that ice soft
I worked 19 years in Manhattan in
diamond company and we had a big boss in
the company a woman and she would often
be agitated or angry and there was a
joke in the company I think she was the
only one who didn't know about it
we had about 800 people in the building
and outside her office if you're going
to see her people would say how's the
weather today can you give me a weather
report and it was a joke it meant is she
in a bad mood or Goodman and then people
would say oh I heard on the radio that
it might rain today it's a little stormy
and it was a secret way of all the
employees to stay don't go in her office
right now so let's take a weather report
about my own mind is it how does it look
this morning you know did I get a good
sleep
it's my jet lag doing ok how how's my
mental weather report this morning
before I start meditating after the
breath let's get a weather report on our
own mind so spend a few minutes just
relax
have fun watch the mind and get a
weather report how does it how does it
how does the mind this morning how
peaceful its my mind this morning here
we go couple of minutes ok you might
think of other things that's part of the
weather report
and then come back let's see how's my
mind this morning
how quiet is my mind this morning don't
try to do anything about it just get a
weather report
now the subject of the lamrim the steps
of the path to enlightenment for this
session this week is called cliche
pleasure is the Sanskrit word it's the
root of one English word called Holly
which is a plant you can see it around
here and it has spines prickly leaves
they don't stick into your hand like
cactus but they feel bad sharp if you
hold the leaf in your hand and it pokes
your hand it it's not like a wound in
your hand but it's uncomfortable and it
so clash' means negative thought in your
mind some negative thought in your mind
and we're going to study them for a week
and the definition of ecclesia iranian
dengue Kanzaki some goon mushiya chapter
symptoms Simba and your monkey teeny the
definition of a negative emotion and
Buddhism is any thought that goes to the
mind and which disturbs the peace of
mind of the person who has it so it's
like the weather inside is very very
quiet and calm and then some wind starts
to blow you can think of a lake the
surface of a lake and your minds natural
condition it's like a quiet leg
and the surface of the lake is like a
mirror in I used to surf a lot in the
early morning just after dawn the ocean
is like that we call glassy it looks
like glass because there's no wind yet
the earth hasn't heated up faster than
the ocean so there's no winds and we
call glassy so the natural condition of
the mind is little glassy it's smooth
and clearing and then when a question
comes when a negative emotion comes then
it stirs up the glassy water and then
you get we call chopped in English
choppy waves small waves on the water it
hurts the surfing so we're gonna do an
experiment this morning and then we'll
take a break okay so we're not gonna go
too long but uh look at your mind now we
took a weather report and it's glassy
normally when we wake up if we've had a
good sleep if the mind is glossy it's
kind of neutral a smooth and that's why
it's good time to meditate in the
morning because the mind is naturally
more glassy smooth but then
we think of things we have to do during
the day and inevitably of course we
start to think of challenges in our life
so we're gonna do an experiment this
morning we're gonna focus on the glassy
mind mind as it is smooth undisturbed
and then purposely we're gonna bring in
a windstorm and I'll help you with that
okay I'll help you to ruin the peace of
your mind
so here we go focus on the mind stay
inside and it's quiet quiet water smooth
glassy enjoy the mind and feel the peace
and calm of the glassy mind just for a
few minutes
stomach is still slightly tighten
inhales are still going higher in the
head faces and fingers are still soft
exhales are still conscious
look at the glassy water of the mind
natural smooth mine
try not to move because when we move we
disturb the other people around this
now maybe for the first time in your
life let's purposely caused a storm in
the mind let's purposely disturb the
glassy water so all of us in our life
each week some challenge comes up maybe
it's a person in your life who is giving
you some problems okay
maybe it's a situation in your health
maybe it's a problem with your husband
or wife or people you work with
I'd like you to purposely go to a
uncomfortable place and ruin the glossy
peaceful water purposely so now you're
gonna do meditation single-pointed ik
agura single pointedly focus on someone
who's giving you trouble nowadays it
changes from week to week year to year
different people give us trouble it
seems very very important at the time
one year later we can't remember
anything about it what's your bad
weather this week this month who's
giving you trouble
and let's focus on them and that's
destroyed the peace of mind let's bring
a wind storm across the water and don't
let it go if you start thinking about
breakfast or lunch bring back your focus
we're not meditating on our Lama
we're not meditating on Amitabha we're
meditating on someone who really
irritates me
make a list of all the things they did
to bother you
don't stop there must be a few more
things they did here
now I'd like you to come back to your
breath observe the breath three long
exhales don't open your eyes don't move
keep your discipline in meditation until
the last moment
then slowly open your eyes take a
stretch I'm gonna take questions if
anybody has questions about meditation
and if someone has to pee pee go ahead
okay so I'd like to not take a longer
break so if you have to pee pee just go
ahead
maybe I'll go and then in the meantime
we'll do some questions okay you got
Joel has a microphone and Joel's gonna
pick so it's his fault if he doesn't
pick you hang on here we go try try
again
good that's fine Oh
whoever irritates you most okay if it's
yourself that's that's great okay so no
problem by the way it could also be a
situation you know it could be the
weather at Diamond Mountain or it could
be the hot water you don't have in your
shower stuff like that okay that the
point of the meditation was to observe a
cliche we want to see what does a clay
should do to me and it's been our whole
life we've been having them every few
hours and we just never noticed what
they do and they stir up them mine okay
that's also in this meditation your goal
is to find something irritating and if
it's a problem to find them you're a
very special person okay about yourself
is fine I want you guys to observe what
a pleasure does to you you know cuz
you've had it your whole life
me too but you didn't notice what it
does to okay okay other question
thank you for making me uncomfortable
[Music]
yeah it's just something I've been
working on and when you teach okay this
is a teacher training it's a rich source
of things to talk about if you've been
working on yourself you know like you
can share with your students
little breakthroughs their little
discoveries you made yourself and in my
opinion as a teacher it'll be more
passionate and more interesting for your
students if you talk about your own
troubles your own problems
your own challenges honestly not in a
you know if you've been working on
something this week bring it up in your
class you know find a way to bring it up
in your class because you're gonna be
more passionate about it so I've just
been working on that I came back from
China with a bad head cold
and then I was observing and you have
little stalks it's like the hell realms
you have little stacks here of sinus
cavity and and you can either bypass
them right or you can consciously try to
breathe up and it's like in yoga the
some of the yoga text says that the
palette is an important part of the body
there's whole schools of yoga that think
the palette is very important somehow
and I'm curious about that so I was just
checking it out and I think if your
sinus cavities are totally free and if
you're consciously ventilating into them
it affects your prana in up here so
check it out so sometimes you just tell
your students I've been messing around
with that I think there's something
there I'm not sure yet
right and then it's more fun for
everybody so I'm just working on it
okay other question I I do believe more
oxygen will get to your brain somehow
check it out louder I'll eat the
microphone
yeah cool so the question was you know
chronic pain like a steady pain in your
back steady pain in your lower back
steady painting your hips pain that
seems to stay with you for long periods
of time in most okay you're learning to
be a teacher right you can always answer
a question on two levels one is what we
call shallow causes you know I could
tell you to take hydrocodone just before
you meditate you know some opioid that's
a shallow cause or I could say look at
the seeds that are causing the the pain
and you know as a what-do-you-call-it
you're catching me at a good time in my
life because I not see now yeah I don't
think and but of course you never know
because once you get there you don't
realize but I've had 40 years of
teaching 40 45 years of teaching so in
my opinion as a teacher to help you give
answers right mix it up mix up the
shallow cause and the deep cause talk
about both okay why it's not very
satisfying to a student if you just keep
saying work on your seats you know like
they're like yeah I guess not I know but
I have a chronic pain so in my opinion
an effective answer should you know from
many years of trying to answer questions
mix it up you know give the person an
answer on a shallow level
and give the person an answer on a deep
level and try to connect them because in
the end the opioid was created by your
karma also by your sins you see what I
mean um the shallow causes also come
from the deep causes okay so connect
them when you give an answer connect
them so I would work on your chronic
pain on two levels number one there's a
whole support system for your body how
you eat how you sit whether you do some
kind of exercise every day and and those
are those are something we do here you
know we're gonna do yoga after
meditation and every the old people me
and John we just do it every day
okay we're just doing yoga every day he
just got back from I don't know he
traveled around the world like three
times last month he's 70 right 71 now
and and my doctor one of my doctors gave
him a checkup
and not long ago and said he has the
healthiest human body of everything and
it's just from daily practice you know
he doesn't let go of he's like a dog
that won't let go of it you try to take
his meditation or he's like yeah
John let's go out for breakfast alright
I do my militating just a normal relaxed
habit of stretching everyday we we have
a program Connie's in charge of it in
Mexico right some of you guys are here
[Music]
too we kind of got permission from the
Congress to teach our stuff to 23
million
kids which may be the biggest thing we
ever did
and so we've been struggling for a name
for the program and we had 23 names
already
and the latest name okay I'm not sure
it's kind of stick or not it's a green
stretch pen GSP so here's the green the
green is just getting to habit of having
a green drink every morning okay stretch
means don't even do yoga just stretch we
don't want to call it yoga yoga has all
these connotations in Hindu you know Oh
mom um you know just stretch your body
every day the pen
yeah it's think about seeds that's all
the whole program for 23 million kids is
green stretch pen right it kind of rolls
off your mouth honey I keep trying to
sell it to her those three things okay
green stretch and pen really have a
green drink every morning friended me
and JB are really what do you call
advocates of a green drink it does
something to you it really it really
does some to you it's not so hard I mean
it tastes like crap and not that I ever
ate crap but uh but okay
just drink wine and stretch every day
you know we had a yoga class on the way
down here we always stop and rent a yoga
room on the way from our house to
Diamond Mountain because it's such a
long drive and we had all kinds of
people in the room some people just had
a hip operation you know okay you don't
have to do a headstand you know somebody
else can do the headstand just stretch
just stretch your body cuz blood will
get into okay those are
those are shallow causes right green and
stretch and then there's what was the
third one
yeah pin okay and then you know help
other people with chronic pain okay
like to serve them and and really serve
them don't do it in a half-assed way
okay like choose one person who has
chronic pain and become their chronic
pain buddy and talk about chronic pain
and talk about new kinds of crappy green
drinks and you know just become their
buddy you know not not visit them once
every two weeks that's what I tell DCI
people because they're not serious okay
so you know be a resource for them these
someone they can depend on be someone
who cares about their chronic pain what
happens when you have chronic pain is
you tell people three times and then
they don't want to hear they don't want
to hear about it you know so be the
person who is gonna follow up on their
chronic pain we had a one of our group
burned their hand very badly last week
very badly it may have to be cut off and
and Jigme just keeps helping her and
she's busy Jigme is trying to run a
retreat etc teacher training and she's
really busy but she decided I'm gonna be
the responsible I'm gonna take care of
this person I don't care you know I'm
busy I'm crazy busy but this person is
gonna lose their hand if I don't help
you know and nobody else wants to
because the person so cranky okay so so
don't let it go don't let the person go
either you know like don't let your
green drink girl go and don't let your
daily stretch go some kind of stretching
okay even if you can't do yoga and then
find a person to latch onto
and be their go-to person okay be the
person who takes care of them cool
that's deep causes and shallow causes
which are deep pin okay rich eyeshadow
mm-hmm it's gonna work honey see it
sticks in people's mind okay
one more question nope
boo catchy
hmm is it sad tears or happy tears are
just water - that's good
Oh me ah you know so I keep telling you
I'm an old man
and I've seen a lot of things in my life
and generally there's an ancient Roman
saying that tears are very precious like
pearls okay so if you can cry sometimes
it's a very good sign
it's a very good thing sad or happy
pearls
are you translating Oh something else
tells me okay
like pearls precious like pearls there's
an old Roman saying they are like
precious like pearls it means you have
feelings and you care about people and
so I think it's a beautiful thing and
just drink a lot of water
[Laughter]
okay here we go I were in the desert
word can't you I can't loose a lot of
water
okay Tim we're gonna go to the alarm
room okay like do you want to take a
pee-pee break let's take it let's take
an official pee pee bring okay 15
minutes come back at 8:55
I'm gonna start at 8:55 if you're not
here I don't care okay